<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://dakotamurray.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://dakotamurray.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-08-04T11:54:28+00:00</updated><id>https://dakotamurray.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Dakota Murray</title><subtitle>personal description</subtitle><author><name>Dakota Murray</name><email>dakota.s.murray@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Science was self-correcting all along</title><link href="https://dakotamurray.me/posts/2022/02/self-correction-in-science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science was self-correcting all along" /><published>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dakotamurray.me/posts/2022/02/self-correction-in-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dakotamurray.me/posts/2022/02/self-correction-in-science/">&lt;p&gt;Reports of the death of self-correction have been greatly exaggerated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common narrative of self-correction is that, in the beginning, mistakes are made, such as errors in analysis, incorrect or incomplete theories, or outright fraud; yet over time, these errors are discovered, fixed, and thus science inches ever closer to truth. But many scholars have grown critical of this narrative, pointing to the ongoing replication crisis and arguing that &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26168125/&quot;&gt;science is not necessarily self-correcting&lt;/a&gt; at all. Fortunately, in response to this crisis, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/future-perfect/21504366/science-replication-crisis-peer-review-statistics&quot;&gt;steps are being taken to try and fix science&lt;/a&gt;, with tools like pre-registration, new approaches to statistical analysis, and more. Time will tell whether these changes will have a positive effect, but there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-018-07118-1&quot;&gt;early signs of progress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this narrative is wrong. Science was self-correcting all along. More than that, imaging science as broken is misleading, because is pre-supposes ways to “fix” science, when the reality is much more complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My argument for why science was always self-correcting is pretty simple. There were problems in science, and scientists (the critics) pointed them out, and now problems are being resolved. So those critics, but pointing out issues in science, proved themselves wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common narrative of self-correction implies that scientific communities naturally police themselves. I don’t think this view is wrong, but I do think it is incomplete. It isn’t that self-policing is distributed across communities, but rather that certain members of scientific communities become the police. Some, like John Ioannidis, Elizabeth Bik, Guillaume Cabanac, and others, independently adopt the role of identifying errors and issues within their scientific fields (or science as a whole), and calling attention to them. Scholars might even be rewarded for adopting this role, with more citations, fame, and respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science was self-correcting all along. It just took a while for some individuals to naturally adopt the role of “police” in response to ongoing issues. They may have done so out of their own ideals, but they may also be rewarded for their efforts, in the form of new fame and access to a broad audience interested in scientific integrity. I see no reason why this process will stop, either. In the future, new issues in science will be discovered, some scholars will self-select into the “police”, and issues will be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in a sense, the critics of self-correcting science prove themselves wrong, because it is their own actions that serve to correct science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still massive problems in science. bad incentives promote flashy yet poorly-evidenced findings over rigorous research and integrity. Studies that fail to replicate are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.abd1705&quot;&gt;cited just as much, if not more&lt;/a&gt; than others. Journals are not held to account for retractions or bad science. Replications continue to fail. And yet, progress is being made, even if it is slow and uneven. Science has the capacity to identify problems and seek changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is important to realize that science has always been self-correcting. To claim otherwise only contributes to a legitimacy crisis of science, leading both scholars and lay people to dismiss whole swathes of research out of hand. Moreover, starting from the position that science is not self-correcting may lead to policies that are counterproductive—quick schemes to “fix” science, or else measures that burden scientists, with little payoff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of worrying about the &lt;em&gt;existence&lt;/em&gt; of self-correction, we should instead concern ourselves with more practical questions, such as how to improve the integrity of knowledge as its produced, or how to speed up and better reward self-correction. These are problems that require trade-offs, often requiring spending limited resources and taxing the time of scientists. Discussing these trade-offs, though, will contribute to a better kind of science.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dakota Murray</name><email>dakota.s.murray@gmail.com</email></author><category term="self-correction" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html">Reports of the death of self-correction have been greatly exaggerated.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is the right way to teach science?</title><link href="https://dakotamurray.me/posts/2022/02/teaching-basics-of-science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is the right way to teach science?" /><published>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dakotamurray.me/posts/2022/02/teaching-basics-of-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dakotamurray.me/posts/2022/02/teaching-basics-of-science/">&lt;p&gt;Are we taught the wrong things about science?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had this thought while watching a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4sLWRScmfH0&quot;&gt;YouTube video by the science communicator Dr. Simon Clark&lt;/a&gt;. In it, he summarized some insights after reading the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/news/the-top-100-papers-1.16224&quot;&gt;top 100 science papers of all time&lt;/a&gt;. But it wasn’t the 100 papers that piqued my interest, but rather Dr. Clark’s explanation of something that has become so fundamental to my academic career: citations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These 100 papers are ranked by citation count. While the symbolic and practical meaning of citations is clear to me, thanks to my career &amp;amp; research, it is not so obvious to the average person. Dr. Clark correctly recognized as much, and spent the first seconds of his video explaining what citations are and what they signify.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Citations are an everyday feature of science that the public likely knows nothing about except for some long-lost knowledge of MLA in school. In fact, the public knows very little about the everyday features of science—my parents couldn’t describe the first thing about what I do all day, let alone anything about academic publishing, tenure, grant funding, or research design. In my experience, many don’t even realize that professors do research at all, instead imagining them as overpaid teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one needs to know the day-to-day minutia of most professions. Not many people need to know what kinds of bookkeeping software accountants use, or the exact process of repairing a pothole in a highway. Yet science is unique, because to critically engage with science—as we should encourage in an educated and democratic society—requires also understanding its minutia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists routinely assess the credibility of a study, by means of where it is published, if it was later retracted or corrected, if the authors are from reputable institutions, whether its funding might produce conflicts of interest, and so much more. How is the average person, even a well educated one, expected to evaluate a study when they have never been taught about the day-to-day work of how science gets done? Even something as straightforward as a paper’s citation count, a deeply flawed yet still essential feature of quality and acceptance, is alien to most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sympathetic to &lt;a href=&quot;https://anarcosurrealisti.noblogs.org/files/2010/10/Feyerabend-Paul-How-to-defend-society-against-science.pdf&quot;&gt;Paul Feyerabend’s warnings of a society&lt;/a&gt; where scientists act as priests speaking inarguable truths from a position of authority. Yet at the same time, as the problems our society face grow in number and complexity, and scientific knowledge becomes more essential to solving them, some amount of authority and respect for science is necessary. What I want is for people to have the tools and background to critically engage with science and scientific knowledge, and this includes knowing about things like citations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my ideal society, science education in school would focus much less on the “scientific method” and rote memory of facts, and more about the work of what scientists themselves do, including things like academic publishing, devising a research program and writing a study, and what is a citation. And I believe that by learning to engage with scientific knowledge as scientists themselves do, that people will also gain a healthy respect for the scientific process that sits at the heart of so many important problems that we face as a society. I want to thank Dr. Simon Clark for the valuable work he has been doing to bring this kind of understanding to people.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dakota Murray</name><email>dakota.s.murray@gmail.com</email></author><category term="science education" /><category term="science communication" /><category term="metrics" /><summary type="html">Are we taught the wrong things about science?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Surviving backlash in science</title><link href="https://dakotamurray.me/posts/2022/02/backlash-in-science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Surviving backlash in science" /><published>2022-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dakotamurray.me/posts/2022/02/backlash-in-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dakotamurray.me/posts/2022/02/backlash-in-science/">&lt;p&gt;What does it take to survive backlash in science?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to make people angry in science. Say the wrong thing to the wrong people, and it’s easy to get people angry. I’m talking here specifically about backlash to scientific arguments that fall under legitimate scientific discourse. I view conflicts like these as mostly good—conflict begets progress. But backlash can also be damaging to a person’s career and psyche, especially when those with power punish any who disagree. I’ve had the chance to watch some different cases of backlash unfold thanks to the enormous amount of time I’ve spent (wasted) on Twitter since the start of the pandemic. I think that by summarizing a few of these, it’s possible to take away some kind of insight about what the effects of backlash, and how to survive it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to provoke backlash is to explicitly attack the ideas of a big name. For an example, consider &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/GidMK&quot;&gt;Gideon Meyerowitz-Katz&lt;/a&gt;, an epidemiological PhD student at the University of Wollongong. This young researcher took the brave, and maybe even risky step of publishing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1201971220321809&quot;&gt;meta-review&lt;/a&gt; that criticized the work of an incredibly famous Stanford professor John Ioannidis. The criticism was levied at Ioannidis’ &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33716331/&quot;&gt;modeling of COVID-19 fatality rates&lt;/a&gt;, models that underpinned his own &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statnews.com/2020/03/17/a-fiasco-in-the-making-as-the-coronavirus-pandemic-takes-hold-we-are-making-decisions-without-reliable-data/&quot;&gt;opposition to lockdowns&lt;/a&gt; and which earned him appearances on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33716331/&quot;&gt;Fox News&lt;/a&gt; to argue against mitigations. Ioannidis published a response to this meta-review which &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/CT_Bergstrom/status/1376080062131269634&quot;&gt;included a personal attack on Meyerowitz-Katz&lt;/a&gt;, insulting his experience and credentials. In many situations, this could have been a devastating career blow. Yet, fortunately, Meyerowitz-Katz handled his &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gidmk/status/1376304539897237508?lang=en&quot;&gt;response&lt;/a&gt; well. The backlash he did receive came largely from one person, whereas he received &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/CT_Bergstrom/status/1376080062131269634&quot;&gt;support from other famous scientists&lt;/a&gt; and gained many &lt;a href=&quot;https://socialblade.com/twitter/user/gidmk&quot;&gt;new followers on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists can get things wrong—variables are left out, data is messy, and mistakes get made. Ideally, science corrects itself and converges towards truth over time. But it’s much harder to do so when there is outright fraud, and when attempts to correct it are met with threats. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MicrobiomDigest&quot;&gt;Elizabeth Bik&lt;/a&gt;, a microbiologist by training, now spends much of her time attempting to identify signals of image manipulation in published papers and notifies journal editors in an attempt to remedy the scientific record. What she does is a great service to the scientific community, resulting in &lt;a href=&quot;https://retractionwatch.com/2019/05/07/meet-elisabeth-bik-who-finds-problematic-images-in-scientific-papers-for-free/&quot;&gt;retractions and corrections&lt;/a&gt; of fraudulent and suspicious works. It is also the kind of work that generates many enemies in the the authors of fraudulent work that Bik uncovers. She has been the target of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/science/2021/aug/03/microbiologist-elisabeth-bik-queried-covid-research-thats-when-the-abuse-and-trolling-began&quot;&gt;harassment&lt;/a&gt; and even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-01430-z&quot;&gt;lawsuits&lt;/a&gt;. Without the financial and legal support of a university or organization, Bik is especially vulnerable to these kinds of threats. Fortunately for science, she is still active in sleuthing for scientific malpractice, establishing herself as a prominent figure into the growing &lt;em&gt;scientific integrity&lt;/em&gt; community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other cases, a person can kick a hornet’s nest without realizing. For instance, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cesarhidalgo.com/&quot;&gt;César Hidalgo&lt;/a&gt; studies complexity science and economics, and has an envious resume brimming with accomplishments. However, even without meaning to, he found himself the target of disagreement by crossing the near-impenetrable boundary that isolates Economics from other disciplines. In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cesifoti/status/1364699994012459009?lang=en&quot;&gt;Twitter thread posted in February of 2021&lt;/a&gt;, Hidalgo outlined how his methods of research—applying Physics and Complex Systems to study economic phenomena—was met with derision by the Economics community, effectively marginalizing him, likely &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cesifoti/status/1494369809538195456&quot;&gt;costing him tenure&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cesifoti/status/1494658744403300355&quot;&gt;delaying important life plans&lt;/a&gt;.  Fortunately, this toxicity did not push Hidalgo out of academia entirely, as he continues to do work at the University of Toulouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can these cases tell us about surviving backlash? First, having a receptive audience is essential. Meyerowitz-Katz opinions represented many epidemiologists, ensuring that he had a well of support once the backlash erupted. But this level of baked-in support is probably rare. Having diverse audiences stretching across multiple communities leads to a more robust social position. If backlash burns bridges in one field, then having the support of another distinct community can provide support in the form of employment, collaboration, and resources. If Hidalgo was a classically-trained economic, the consequences of the backlash would have been more dire; fortunately, he approached economics from his home discipline of complex systems, cushioning the brunt of backlash. When these fail, then credibility and integrity are essential; Bik has cultivated these traits and thus has an inscrutable reputation ensuring that she can garner broad support of many even as she faces legal threats. At the same time, she has carved out a new audience, one interested in scientific integrity that stretches across all fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its important to note that these cases are the survivors of backlash. There is an entire hidden side of science consisting of people whose careers were diminished or destroyed due to an argument with their advisor or a prominent scholar assaulting their reputation. Those most vulnerable to backlash will be from marginalized communities, such as women and people of color. Their voices and perspectives are then lost, leading to a duller, less dynamic, and less effective science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backlash isn’t just about gossip and academic drama. The process of making knowledge is inherently contentious. The disagreements, critiques, disputes, and challenges between scientists are bloody but necessary—it leads to progress. When pettiness prevents disagreements from happening or punishes those who raise their voice, it diminishes science. The best science is chaotic and discordant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dakota Murray</name><email>dakota.s.murray@gmail.com</email></author><category term="backlash" /><category term="disagreement" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html">What does it take to survive backlash in science?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Defending my dissertation</title><link href="https://dakotamurray.me/posts/2021/08/final-dissertation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Defending my dissertation" /><published>2021-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dakotamurray.me/posts/2021/08/final-dissertation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dakotamurray.me/posts/2021/08/final-dissertation/">&lt;p&gt;Well, I did it! I wrote my dissertation. I’m Dr. Murray now. A year of pre-k. 12 years of grade school. 5 years for my undergraduate degree. 5 more for this PhD. 23 years of my life have been spent in school! It’s a strange, scary, and exhilarating feeling to have finally reached the zenith of this long experience, and to stare into the distance ahead, wondering what’s next. The next steps, however, will have to wait. First, I want to catch my breath and look back at this latest achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I titled my dissertation &lt;em&gt;Embracing Complexity in the Science of Science&lt;/em&gt;.
Its a “stapled” dissertation format, merging 4 studies that I wrote while in grad school. The narrative thread I chose to connect each study was to look at science through the perspective of Complexity Science, considering how treating science as a complex system might inform us about its inner workings. You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.proquest.com/docview/2585951948?pq-origsite=gscholar&amp;amp;fromopenview=true&quot;&gt;read it here&lt;/a&gt;, if you want (its quite long). If you’re more of a visual person, you might also appreciate &lt;a href=&quot;slides/dissertation_presentation&quot;&gt;this presentation&lt;/a&gt;, which I think did a pretty good job of summarizing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first of the four studies investigates the extent of gender and national bias in peer review, observing the role of &lt;em&gt;homophilic preferences&lt;/em&gt; in not only shaping review decisions, but structuring the composition of teams of referees.
The second study leverages public and private data to explore the factors driving student-teacher evaluations, an important but often overlooked metric in a scientist’s career; we find evidence of &lt;em&gt;demographic bias&lt;/em&gt;, namely that women and non-White faculty are at a disadvantage in these ratings, putting them at a disadvantage in hiring, promotion, and more. The third study attempts to quantify the extent of disagreement across science, revealing that it is most common in the social sciences and humanities, and lowest in physics and maths; yet there is also a great deal of heterogeneity across sub-fields, resulting from their the &lt;em&gt;physical realities&lt;/em&gt; of their research topic. Finally, the fourth study explores the examines the global landscape of scientific mobility, creating a dense representation of mobility that illustrates the importance of different kinds of &lt;em&gt;proximities&lt;/em&gt;, such as geography, language, culture, shared history, and prestige, in structuring the mobility decisions of individual scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, each of these studies constitutes a significant contribution to the Science of Science. Yet when viewed collectively through the perspective of complex systems, they show insights about the organization and behavior of science. For example, &lt;em&gt;homophilic preferences&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;demographic bias&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;physical realities&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;proximity&lt;/em&gt; are all examples of &lt;em&gt;bottom-up forces&lt;/em&gt; that govern the actions and interactions of individuals, allowing them to self-organize into complex social arrangements such as teams, communities, and disciplines. Concepts like &lt;em&gt;feedback&lt;/em&gt;, too, explain how selection mechanisms, like peer review (eLife), metric evaluations (student-teacher evaluations), peer judgements (disagreement), and hiring (mobility) naturally produce and perpetuate inequalities and hierarchies in science. Yet feedback also allows for radical change across science. The &lt;em&gt;chaotic&lt;/em&gt; nature of science sometimes triggers feedback loops that amplify the effects of certain events, such as an individual’s success or a breakthrough discovery, to such an extreme that they remake wide swathes of science over a few short years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By viewing science as a complex system, it shifts the attention of the Science of Science away from grand theories of science and universal laws, and instead towards the everyday actions and behaviors of individual scientists. By simply shifting our perspective, we can reveal something about the fundamental workings of science, and maybe even spot a path towards improving it, making it more open, equitable, and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are of course tons of details left in my dissertation. Writing it took a long time, many revisions, and a lot of reading! Although I have wonderful mentors who praised my work, I remain intimately familiar with all of its shortcomings. Yet finally, I am beginning to look back and appreciate the work I have produced. It will never be perfect, but it was good enough to get me to where I want to go. And I’ve learned a lot from it too. I hope to take what I learned here and do even better research moving forward, because the dissertation shouldn’t be a barrier to your career, but a stepping stone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dakota Murray</name><email>dakota.s.murray@gmail.com</email></author><category term="dissertation" /><category term="career" /><category term="PhD" /><summary type="html">Well, I did it! I wrote my dissertation. I’m Dr. Murray now. A year of pre-k. 12 years of grade school. 5 years for my undergraduate degree. 5 more for this PhD. 23 years of my life have been spent in school! It’s a strange, scary, and exhilarating feeling to have finally reached the zenith of this long experience, and to stare into the distance ahead, wondering what’s next. The next steps, however, will have to wait. First, I want to catch my breath and look back at this latest achievement.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Graph Laplacian Eigenmaps</title><link href="https://dakotamurray.me/posts/2019/16/graph-laplacian-eigenmaps/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Graph Laplacian Eigenmaps" /><published>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dakotamurray.me/posts/2019/16/graph-laplacian-eigenmaps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dakotamurray.me/posts/2019/16/graph-laplacian-eigenmaps/">&lt;p&gt;Graph laplacian eigenmaps (GLE) are one means, among many, of embedding graphs into a low-dimensional numeric space. Specifically, GLE is an approach based on Matrix Factorization that takes as input non-relational data and outputs node embeddings. The key insight of GLEs is that the graph property to be preserved can be interpreted as pairwise node similarities. Thus, a larger penalty is imposed if two nodes with large similarity are embedded far apart. Thus, the goal of this approach is to find an embedding that minimizes this penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gist of this approach is that it aims to first represent the graph as a Graph Laplacian Matrix, $L$. $L$ is a means of representing a graph in matrix form following the definition $L = D - W$, where $D$ is the &lt;em&gt;degree matrix&lt;/em&gt;, a diagonal matrix containing the degree of each node, and $W$ is the adjacency matrix of weights. Under this representation, all positive values correspond to degrees of the node, and all negative values to the weights of the edges. We then perform a decomposition on $L$ to find its eigenvalues. The eigenvectors corresponding to the smallest of the eigenvalues are used as the embedding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The optimal embedding, $y^{\ast}$ can be derived from the following objective function,&lt;/p&gt;

\[y^{\ast} = \text{argmin}\_{y} \sum\_{i\neq j} (y\_{i} - y\_{j}^{2} W\_{ij}) = \text{argmin}\_{y} y^{T}Ly\]

&lt;p&gt;Where $W_{ij}$ is the similarity matrix between every pair of nodes $v_{i}$ and $v_{j}$. $L$ is the graph laplacian matrix, $D$ is the diagonal matrix for which $D_{ii} = \sum_{i \neq j}W_{ij}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this objective function is to find the embedding, $y^{\ast}$ that minimizes the error compared to the Graph Laplacian Matrix, $L$. One benefit of representing a graph with $L$ rather than a simple adjacency matrix is that the diagonal will contain the degrees of the graph; the larger the degree of a node, the more that its row will be “weighted” when computing the objective function. The practical effect is that larger degree nodes will have a greater impact on the embedding than lower-degree nodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several expansions on this basic optimization, but in each of these variants, the optimal embedding $y^{\prime}$ are the eigenvectors of the laplacian matrix, $\lambda$, which can be calculated by solving the the eigenproblem $Wy = \lambda Dy$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arrange the eigenvalues from smallest to largest. The first eigenvalue should be close to zero, and its corresponding eigenvector is not typically used for embedding. Rather, use the remaining eigenvalues and their corresponding eigenvectors to construct the $d$-dimensional embedding. For example, a 3-dimensional embedding can be constructed using the eigenvectors corresponding to the 2nd, 3rd, and 4th smallest eigenvalues. A 2-dimensional embedding can be constructed using the eigenvectors of the 2nd and 3rd smallest eigenvalues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets walk through this process in R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the Karate network, shown below, which is a popular network exemplifying community structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post_images/graph_laplacian_eigenmaps/karate_graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having loaded this data into R, we can construct the Graph Laplacian Matrix, $L$, from the adjacency matrix $W$ and the degree matrix, $D$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;W &amp;lt;- as.matrix(as.matrix.network(karate))
D &amp;lt;- diag(rowSums(W))
L &amp;lt;- D - W
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, we can solve the eigenproblem $Wy = \lambda Dy$ and select the eigenvectors corresponding to the 2nd and 3rd smallest eigenvectors to produce an embedding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;eig &amp;lt;- eigen(L, D)
col_dim &amp;lt;- dim(eig$vectors)[1]
vectors &amp;lt;- eig$vectors[,(col_dim - 1):(col_dim - 2)]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting embedding is shown below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post_images/graph_laplacian_eigenmaps/karate_embed.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see that much of the structure from the original graph also appears in the embedding. As with the network, the embedding demonstrates a clear division between the two communities. Additionally, we see all the nodes that are directly connected to the opposing community are clustered together. Meanwhile, nodes for Actor 5, 6, 7, 11, and 17 are clustered apart form the other clusters, reflecting their somewhat isolated position in the original graph. Similarly, Actor 12 only maintains one connection to Mr. H, and is thus set far apart from the other nodes in the embedding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many uses for graph embeddings. They allow for fast computation of node distances and can serve as effective features for graph-based classification problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This content was largely drawn from the following resources,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cai, H., Zheng, V. W., &amp;amp; Chang, K. C.-C. (2017). A Comprehensive Survey of Graph Embedding: Problems, Techniques and Applications. ArXiv:1709.07604 [Cs]. Retrieved from https://arxiv.org/abs/1709.07604&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Belkin, M., &amp;amp; Niyogi, P. (2001). Laplacian Eigenmaps and Spectral Techniques for Embedding and Clustering. Proceedings of the 14th International Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems: Natural and Synthetic, 585–591. Retrieved from https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2980539.2980616&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Dakota Murray</name><email>dakota.s.murray@gmail.com</email></author><category term="embedding" /><category term="networks" /><summary type="html">Graph laplacian eigenmaps (GLE) are one means, among many, of embedding graphs into a low-dimensional numeric space. Specifically, GLE is an approach based on Matrix Factorization that takes as input non-relational data and outputs node embeddings. The key insight of GLEs is that the graph property to be preserved can be interpreted as pairwise node similarities. Thus, a larger penalty is imposed if two nodes with large similarity are embedded far apart. Thus, the goal of this approach is to find an embedding that minimizes this penalty.</summary></entry></feed>